<entry eid="00002" hw="aa1 naa4"><hw eid="00002_hw_1" >吖嗱</hw><ps>M.P.</ps><var>a.p.a. aa1 laa4; a.w.a. 吖喇 aa1 laa3/4</var><s1 n="1"><seealso>吖 aa1, 嗱 naa4</seealso><df eid="00002_df_1" >speaker makes a suggestion</df><x-g ><tx eid="00002_tx_1" >唔啱去睇戲吖嗱?</tx><x eid="00002_x_1" >Let's watch a movie then!</x></x-g></s1><s2 n="2"><seealso>㗎喇 gaa3 laa3, 個噃 go3 bo3</seealso><df eid="00002_df_2" >speaker exp. warning</df><s1 n="2.1"><x-g ><tx eid="00002_tx_2" >你試吓再打人吖嗱!</tx><x eid="00002_x_2" >See what happens to you if you beat someone up again!</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2.2"><x-g ><tx eid="00002_tx_3" >你講乜嘢啊頭先?𨳒你老母!我打你老母臭閪吖嗱!</tx><x eid="00002_x_3" >What did you say just now? Fuck your mother! I warn you I'm going to beat you up!</x></x-g></s1></s2><ser>00002</ser><ref>ZN1999:001; LCS2005:012; PGJB20160520PgA4; RSBfmInternet21052016</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="13919" hw="baa2 lan2 me1"><hw eid="13919_hw_1" >把𨶙咩</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><en>coll.; obscene lg.; a.w.p.a. 把X咩 baa2 lan2 me1, 把撚咩 baa2 lan2 me1 (more com. written form and with change in pron. of std. Can. 撚 nan2)</en><seealso>把鬼 baa2 gwai2, 把屁 baa2 pei3, 𨶙 lan2</seealso><df eid="13919_df_1" >completely damn useless!, completely damn pointless!, fucking pointless!</df><s1 n="1"><x-g ><tx eid="13919_tx_1" >啲後生仔嚟見工,乜都冇準備!有啲人相又冇張,筆又唔帶枝,我梗係好嬲!請佢哋嚟把𨶙咩!</tx><x eid="13919_x_1" >The young men came for job interviews without a bit of preparation, some of them didn't have photos, some didn't bring a pen, of course I'm angry, inviting them to come was completely damn useless!</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2"><x-g ><tx eid="13919_tx_2" >佢攪咁𨶙多嘢把𨶙咩?!</tx><x eid="13919_x_2" >Her stirring up so much damn stuff is completely damn useless?!</x></x-g></s1><ser>13919</ser><ref>CE2005:017; HB2005:007; PGJB20160428PgA1; RSBfmInternet29042016</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="12537" hw="bei3/2 zek3 zung1 zi2"><hw eid="12537_hw_1" >畀隻中指</hw><ps>V.O.</ps><en>lit. to give (so.) the middle finger; fig.; this off. and obscene hand gesture has been borrowed from Br. cult. and has the same meaning as in the U.K. and U.S.A. for insulting and showing one's anger to or contempt for so.; a.s.a. 舉隻中指畀 geoi2 zek3 zung1 zi2 bei3/2; a.w.a. 俾隻中指 bei2 zek3 zung1 zi2</en><seealso>舉隻中指畀 geoi2 zek3 zung1 zi2 bei3/2</seealso><df eid="12537_df_1" >go to hell!, fuck off!, fuck you!</df><x-g ><tx eid="12537_tx_1" >我見到前面架車冇開燈,就閃佢兩吓高燈,佢都未知咩事,我後來喺佢側邊過時,佢仲畀隻中指我表示佢好嬲!</tx><x eid="12537_x_1" >I saw that the car in front didn't have its lights on. I then flashed my high beams to him twice, but he didn't know why, and later when I was passing on his side, he even gave me the middle finger to show he was quite angry!</x></x-g><ser>12537</ser><ref>RSBfmInternet29072012</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10880" hw="cat6"><hw eid="10880_hw_1" >𨳍</hw><s1 n="1"><ps>N.</ps><mw>碌 luk1, 條 tiu4</mw><note>can be used in verbal abuse; vulg.; off.; a.s.a. 𨳊 gau1, 𨶙 lan2; a.w.a. 𫵱 cat6, 柒 cat1/6</note><seealso>賓周 ban1 zau1, 不文物 bat1 man4 mat6, 𫵱 cat6, 𨳍頭 cat6 tau4, 𨳍頭皮 cat6 tau4 pei4, 扯硬 ce2 ngaang6, 𨳊 gau1, 大碌木 daai6 luk1 muk6, 械 haai6, 起頭 hei2 tau4, 香蕉 hoeng1 ziu1, 𨶙 lan2, 碌嘢 luk1 je5, 是非根 si6 fei1 gan1, 雪茄 syut3 gaa1, 條嘢 tiu4 je5, J zei1, JJ zei1 zei1, 枝嘢 zi1 je5, 子孫根 zi2 syun1 gan1, 蕉 ziu1, 朘 zoe1, 朘朘 zoe1 zoe1, 雀 zoek3/2, 雀仔 zoek3 zai2</seealso><df eid="10880_df_1" >dick, prick, cock, willy, pecker, i.e. man's penis</df><x-g ><tx eid="10880_tx_1" >你笨𨳍!</tx><x eid="10880_x_1" >You're a stupid prick!</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2"><ps>V.</ps><df eid="10880_df_2" >to fool around, dick around, fuck off</df><x-g ><tx eid="10880_tx_2" >你喺度𨳍吓𨳍吓做乜?</tx><x eid="10880_x_2" >What are you doing dicking around here?</x></x-g></s1><ser>10880</ser><ref>ZC1988:204; HFC1995:256; MT1997:048; CB2002:088; LSHK2002:283; HB2005:037</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="13936" hw="ding2 nei5 go3 fai3"><hw eid="13936_hw_1" >頂你個肺</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><en>lit. to press against your lung; fig.; vulg.; speaker exp. anger, irritation, aggression, surprise, amazement; 頂 ding2 may be a EUPH. for 𨳒 diu2 'fuck', and 肺 fai3 a EUPH. for 閪 hai1 'cunt'</en><seealso>頂頸 ding2 geng2, 𨳒 diu2, 𨳒你老味! diu2 nei5 lou5 mei6/2, 𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2, 𨳒你老母臭閪diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2 cau3 hai1, 閪 hai1</seealso><df eid="13936_df_1" >go to hell!, how dare you!, damn you!, fuck you!, shit!</df><x-g ><tx eid="13936_tx_1" >我頂你個肺啊!你想做死人咩?</tx><x eid="13936_x_1" >Go to hell! Do you want to die?</x></x-g><ser>13936</ser><ref>CE2005:226; HB2005:093; RSBfmInternet19062015</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="01086" hw="diu1"><hw eid="01086_hw_1" >丟</hw><ps>INTJ.</ps><note>orig. word is 屌 diu2 'fuck' which has undergone tone change and substitution with 丟 diu1 'lose' so as to weaken its offensiveness; vulg.</note><seealso>𨳒 diu2, 丟那媽 diu1 naa5 maa1, 丟那媽,頂硬上 diu1 naa5 maa1, ding2 ngaang6 soeng5</seealso><df eid="01086_df_1" >fuck it!</df><ser>01086</ser><ref>ZN1999:047</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10878" hw="diu2"><hw eid="10878_hw_1" >𨳒</hw><ps>V.</ps><en>vulg.; off.; a.s.a. 丟 diu1 which sounds less off.; a.w.a. 屌 diu2</en><seealso>爆房 baau3 fong4/2, 扑一鑊 bok1 jat1 wok6, 扑嘢 bok1 je5, 扑濕 bok1 sap1, 插 caap3, 砌 cai3, 鋤爆 co4 baau3, 丟 diu1, 攪嘢 gaau2 je5, 開鑊 hoi1 wok6, 食 sik6, 㗱 zep6, 𡁻 zeu6, 鑿 zok6, 鑿嘢 zok6 je5, 做嘢 zou6 je5</seealso><s1 n="1"><df eid="10878_df_1" >to fuck</df><x-g ><tx eid="10878_tx_1" >佢想𨳒你條菜</tx><x eid="10878_x_1" >He wants to fuck your girlfriend</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2"><seealso>𨳒開 diu2 hoi1, 𨳒你老母臭閪 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2 cau3 hai1, 𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2</seealso><df eid="10878_df_2" >used in vulg. insults to exp. speaker's hostility, aggression, surprise, amazement, etc.</df></s1><ser>10878</ser><ref>YH1972:258; CB2002:094; ZBH2002a:297; CE2005:230; HB2005:094; MT2011:041</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10879" hw="diu2 hoi1"><hw eid="10879_hw_1" >𨳒開!</hw><ps>V.P.</ps><note>used as vulg. insult to exp. speaker's hostility, aggression, anger, etc.</note><df eid="10879_df_1" >fuck off!, get the hell out of here!</df><ser>10879</ser><ref>CB2002:094; HB2005:094</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="01085" hw="diu1 naa5 maa1"><hw eid="01085_hw_1" >丟那媽</hw><ps>INTJ.</ps><en>lit. to lose your mother; vulg.; der. orig. from 屌你阿媽 diu2 nei5 aa3 maa1 'fuck your mother' with contraction of two syllables 你阿 (a.w.a. 你亞) nei5 aa3 into 那 naa5, along with tone change and substitution of 屌 diu2 with 丟 diu1 'lose', so as to weaken its offensiveness; this was orig. the first part of the two-part battle-cry from 明朝 ming4 ciu4 Ming dynasty (1368 – 1644), for which the second part is 頂硬上 ding2 ngaang6 soeng5 'stubbornly forge ahead'; exp. belongs to the category of 三字經 saam1 zi6 ging1; a.p.a. diu1 naa3 maa1; a.w.a. 刁哪媽 diu1 naa5 maa1, 屌那媽 diu2/1 naa5 maa1, 掉哪媽 diu6/1 naa5 maa1; a.w.p.a. 挑那媽 tiu1 naa5 maa1</en><seealso>丟 diu1, 𨳒 diu2, 丟那媽,頂硬上 diu1 naa5 maa1, ding2 ngaang6 soeng5, 三字經 saam1 zi6 ging1, 挑那媽 tiu1 naa5 maa1, 挑那星 tiu1 naa3 sing1</seealso><df eid="01085_df_1" >fuck it!</df><ser>01085</ser><ref>CTA1997:162; WKB1997:051; ZN1999:047; ZZF2008:196, 279, 311; ROZ2009:047; MT2011:352</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="13263" hw="diu2 naa5 maa1"><hw eid="13263_hw_1" >屌那媽</hw><ps>EXCL.</ps><note>vulg. exp. of anger, irritation; 那 naa5 is contr. of 你阿 nei5 aa3 'your'</note><seealso>丟那媽 diu1 naa5 maa1, 𨳒 diu2, 𨳒你老母臭閪! diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5 cau3 hai1, 挑那星 tiu1 naa5 sing1</seealso><df eid="13263_df_1" >fuck your mother!</df><ser>13263</ser><ref>MT2011:352; RSBfmInternet26012014</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="01084" hw="diu1 naa5 maa1, ding2 ngaang6 soeng5"><hw eid="01084_hw_1" >丟那媽,頂硬上</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><en>lit. to lose your mother, hit the hard; first word was orig. 屌 diu2 'fuck' which underwent tone change and substitution with 丟 diu1 'lose' to weaken its offensiveness; this was orig. the now famous battle-cry assoc. with the patriotic gnl. Yuan Chonghuan 袁崇煥 jyun4 sung4 wun6 (1584-1630 CE) of the Ming 明 ming4 dynasty (1368 – 1644 CE) when he defeated the Manchu chieftain Nurhaci 努爾哈赤 nou5 ji5 haa1 cek3 (1559-1626 CE) in the Battle of Ningyuan 寧袁戰 ning4 jyun4 zin3 in 1626, and thus temporarily halted the Manchu 滿州 mun5 zau1 invasion of Ch.; this exp. was adopted as the rallying cry of pro-Can. demonstrators in GZ. and HK. in July and August 2010; the two parts of the exp. are also used separately as lexical items; 那媽 naa5 maa1 is contr. of 你阿媽 nei5 aa3 maa1 'your mother'; first part a.p.a. diu1 naa3 maa1; a.w.a. 刁哪媽 diu1 naa5 maa1, 掉哪媽 diu6/1 naa5 maa1</en><seealso>丟 diu1, 𨳒 diu2, 丟那媽 diu1 naa5 maa1, 頂硬上 ding2 ngaang6 soeng5, 挑那媽 tiu1 naa5 maa1, 挑那星 tiu1 naa3 sing1</seealso><df eid="01084_df_1" >fuck it!, and stubbornly forge ahead!</df><ser>01084</ser><ref>ZN1999:047</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="04398" hw="diu2 nei5 lou5 mei6/2"><hw eid="04398_hw_1" >𨳒你老味!</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><note>partial EUPH. for 𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2 'fuck your old mother', but still vulg. and obsc. insult; spkeaker exp. surprise, amazement, hostility; a.w.a. 𨳒你鹵味! diu2 nei5 lou5 mei6/2 but less com.</note><seealso>頂你個肺 ding2 nei5 go3 fai3, 𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2, 𨳒你老母臭閪 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2 cau3 hai1, 鹵味 lou5 mei6/2</seealso><df eid="04398_df_1" >fuck your old meat, i.e. fuck your mother!</df><ser>04398</ser><ref>HB2005:094; RSBfmInternet08012015</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10876" hw="diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2"><hw eid="10876_hw_1" >𨳒你老母!</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><note>aggressive, obsc. insult; for some Can. speakers who also know Eng. the Eng. exp. Delay No More can be used as a euphemism to replace this tabooed Can. exp. but with the same meaning implied but toned down; vulg.; off.</note><seealso>頂你個肺 ding2 nei5 go3 fai3, 𨳒你老味! diu2 nei5 lou5 mei6/2, 𨳒你老母臭閪 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2 cau3 hai1, 你老母 nei5 lou5 mou5/2, 問候你老母 man6 hau6 nei5 lou5 mou5/2</seealso><df eid="10876_df_1" >(I) fuck your mother!</df><ser>10876</ser><ref>HB2005:095</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10875" hw="diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2 cau3 hai1"><hw eid="10875_hw_1" >𨳒你老母臭閪!</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><note>non plus ultra of aggressive, obsc. Can. insults; vulg.; off.; a.s.a. 𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2, 𨳒你老母個臭花閪! diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5 go3 cau3 faa1 hai1, 𨳒你老母個臭閪! diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5 go3 cau3 hai1</note><seealso>頂你個肺 ding2 nei5 go3 fai3, 𨳒 diu2, 𨳒你老味! diu2 nei5 lou5 mei6/2, 𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2, 屌那媽 diu2 naa5 maa1, 閪 hai1, 你老母 nei5 lou5 mou5/2, 問候你老豆 man6 hau6 nei5 lou5 dau6, 問候你老母 man6 hau6 nei5 lou5 mou5/2</seealso><df eid="10875_df_1" >(I) fuck your mother's stinking cunt!</df><ser>10875</ser><ref>HB2005:095</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10867" hw="gau1"><hw eid="10867_hw_1" >𨳊</hw><s1 n="1"><ps>N.</ps><mw>碌 luk1, 條 tiu4</mw><note>used in verbal abuse; vulg.; off; a.s.a. 𨳍 cat6, 𨶙 lan2; a.w.a. 尻 gau1, 㞗 gau1, 鳩 gau1</note><seealso>賓周 ban1 zau1, 不文物 bat1 man4 mat6, 𫵱 cat6, 𨳍 cat6, 扯硬 ce2 ngaang6, 大碌木 daai6 luk1 muk6, 大炮 daai6 paau3, 𨳊笠 gau1 lap1, 𨳊毛 gau1 mou4, 𨳊噏 gau1 ngap1, 鳩嗚 gau1 wu1, 械 haai6, 起頭 hei2 tau4, 香蕉 hoeng1 ziu1, 𨶙 lan2, 露械 lou6 haai6, 碌嘢 luk1 je5, 戇𨳊 ngong6 gau1, 戇𨳊𨳊 ngong6 gau1 gau1, 戇𨳊仔 ngong6 gau1 zai2, 戇𨶙𨳊 ngong6 lan2 gau1, 炮 paau3, 是非根 si6 fei1 gan1, 雪茄 syut3 gaa1, 條嘢 tiu4 je5, J zei1, JJ zei1 zei1, 枝嘢 zi1 je5, 子孫根 zi2 syun1 gan1, 蕉 ziu1, 朘 zoe1, 朘朘 zoe1 zoe1, 雀 zoek3/2, 雀仔 zoek3 zai2</seealso><df eid="10867_df_1" >dick, prick, cock, willy, pecker, i.e. male sex organ, man's penis</df><x-g ><tx eid="10867_tx_1" >條女同男友坦白講,你碌𨳊太細,我冇乜感覺</tx><x eid="10867_x_1" >The girl frankly said to her boyfriend, "Your dick is too small, I can't feel anything"</x></x-g></s1><s2 n="2"><ps>INF.</ps><note>used as intensifier in vulg. abuse</note><seealso>𨶙 lan2</seealso><df eid="10867_df_2" >fucking, damn</df><s1 n="2.1"><x-g ><tx eid="10867_tx_2" >真麻𨳊煩!</tx><x eid="10867_x_2" >It's really fucking troublesome!</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2.2"><x-g ><tx eid="10867_tx_3" >你𨳊話做乜?</tx><x eid="10867_x_3" >Why are you talking such damn bullshit?</x></x-g></s1></s2><ser>10867</ser><ref>MW1947:188; YH1972:332; ZC1988:204; HFC1995:256; CTA1997:154; CB2002:101; CE2005:355; HB2005:139; MT2011:037</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="12538" hw="geoi2 zek3 zung1 zi2 bei2"><hw eid="12538_hw_1" >舉隻中指畀</hw><ps>V.O.</ps><en>lit. to give (so.) the middle finger; fig.; this off. and obscene hand gesture has been borrowed from Br. cult. and has the same meaning as in the U.K. and U.S.A. for insulting and showing one's anger to or contempt for so.; a.s.a. 畀隻中指 bei3/2 zek3 zung1 zi2; a.w.a. 舉隻中指俾 geoi2 zek3 zung1 zi2 bei2</en><seealso>畀隻中指 bei3/2 zek3 zung1 zi2</seealso><df eid="12538_df_1" >go to hell!, fuck off!, fuck you!</df><x-g ><tx eid="12538_tx_1" >個司機打開窗伸隻手出車,就舉起隻中指畀我表示佢好嬲!</tx><x eid="12538_x_1" >The driver opened the car window sticking his hand out, and then raised up his middle finger to me to show he was quite angry!</x></x-g><ser>12538</ser><ref>RSBfmInternet29072012</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="03086" hw="hing3 gwo3 fo2 si2"><hw eid="03086_hw_1" >㷫過火屎</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><en>lit. hotter than fire shit; fig.; a.s.a. 㷫過焫雞 hing3 gwo3 naat3 gai1</en><seealso>把火 baa2 fo2, 把幾火 baa2 gei2 fo2, 把鬼火 baa2 gwai2 fo2, 爆火 baau3 fo2, 吹鬚睩眼 ceoi1 sou1 luk1 ngaan5, 火都嚟𠹺 fo2 dou1 lai4 maai4, 火滾 fo2 gwan2, 火遮眼 fo2 ze1 ngaan5, 㷫 hing3, 㷫過焫雞 hing3 gwo3 naat3 gai1, 一肚氣 jat1 tou5 hei3, 焫雞 naat3 gai1, 嬲爆爆 nau1 baau3 baau3, 眼火爆 ngaan5 fo2 baau3, 惡 ok3, 生蝦咁跳 saang1 haa1 gam3 tiu3, 扎扎跳 zaat3 zaat3 tiu3, 撞火 zong6 fo2</seealso><df eid="03086_df_1" >to be very angry, absolutely furious</df><x-g ><tx eid="03086_tx_1" >𨳒你老味!我而𠺢真係㷫過火屎!</tx><x eid="03086_x_1" >Fuck your old meat! I'm now really absolutely furious!</x></x-g><ser>03086</ser><ref>HB2005:183; ZZF2008:372; RSBfmInternet05012015</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="11909" hw="jiu2"><hw eid="11909_hw_1" >妖</hw><ps>INTJ., EUPH.</ps><en>lit. demon, evil and harmful spirit in fable or legend; used in place of vulg. 𨳒 diu2 'fuck'</en><seealso>𨳒 diu2</seealso><df eid="11909_df_1" >heck, shoot, shucks, darn</df><x-g ><tx eid="11909_tx_1" >借錢畀你?妖!借你條𨶙!</tx><x eid="11909_x_1" >Loan money to you? Shoot! I'll loan you shit!</x></x-g><ser>11909</ser><ref>HB2005:459</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="03889" hw="laan1 hoi1"><hw eid="03889_hw_1" >躝開</hw><ps>V.P.</ps><var>a.w.a. 攔開 laan1 hoi1</var><seealso>躝 laan1</seealso><df eid="03889_df_1" >get out of here, fuck off, piss off, go away, leave me alone</df><x-g ><tx eid="03889_tx_1" >你即刻同我躝開!</tx><x eid="03889_x_1" >You get the hell out of here at once and leave me alone!</x></x-g><ser>03889</ser><ref>GHN1984:293; SS2002:159; HB2005:243; RSBfmInternet26082014</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="03990" hw="lam3 dong3"><hw eid="03990_hw_1" >冧檔</hw><ps>V.</ps><s2 n="1"><en>coll.</en><seealso>𢫏斗 kam2 dau2, 𢫏檔 kam2 dong3, 冧 lam3, 收皮 sau1 pei4, 執 zap1, 執笠 zap1 lap1, 執咗 zap1 zo2, 摺𠹺 zip3 maai4</seealso><df eid="03990_df_1" >(for a bus.) to collapse, fail, go bankrupt, cease operations, go under, (for a co.) to go out of bus.; (for computer system) to go down</df><s1 n="1.1"><x-g ><tx eid="03990_tx_1" >有啲人唔鍾意同我競爭，好想我冧檔</tx><x eid="03990_x_1" >Some people don't like competing with me. They want my business to collapse</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="1.2"><x-g ><tx eid="03990_tx_2" >今朝我間銀行有網絡設備故障，引致幾間分行電腦系統冧檔癱瘓喇</tx><x eid="03990_x_2" >This morning my bank had a network equipment glitch. It caused the computer systems in several bank branches to go down and be paralyzed</x></x-g></s1></s2><s1 n="2"><en>sl.</en><seealso>冧 lam3, 冧友 lam3 jau5/2, 死咗 sei2 zo2</seealso><df eid="03990_df_2" >to be finished off, dead</df><x-g ><tx eid="03990_tx_3" >佢呀?打𨶙到冧檔啊!</tx><x eid="03990_x_3" >Him? Fucking beat him till he's dead!</x></x-g></s1><ser>03990</ser><ref>BWR1998:290; ZN1999:191; CE2005:551; HB2005:246; LBC2008:230; MT2011:292; ROZ2016:157; ZNP2018:348; PGJB20190415PgA5</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10869" hw="lan2"><hw eid="10869_hw_1" >𨶙</hw><s1 n="1"><ps>N.</ps><mw>碌 luk1, 條 tiu4</mw><en>vulg.; off.; a.s.a. 𨳍 cat6, 𨳊 gau1; a.w.a. 𠹌 lan2; a.w.p.a. 撚 lan2 with change in pron. of std. Can. nan2</en><seealso>賓周 ban1 zau1, 不文物 bat1 man4 mat6, 𫵱 cat6, 𨳍 cat6, 扯硬 ce2 ngaang6, 大碌木 daai6 luk1 muk6, 大炮 daai6 paau3, 𨳊 gau1, 含𨶙 ham4 lan2, 起頭 hei2 tau4, 香蕉 hoeng1 ziu1, 碌嘢 luk1 je5, 戇𨶙𨳊 ngong6 lan2 gau1, 雪茄 syut3 gaa3, 條嘢 tiu4 je5, J zei1, JJ zei1 zei1, 枝嘢 zi1 je5, 子孫根 zi2 syun1 gan1, 蕉 ziu1, 朘 zoe1, 雀 zoek3/2, 雀仔 zoek3 zai2</seealso><df eid="10869_df_1" >dick, prick, cock, willy, pecker, i.e. man's penis</df></s1><s2 n="2"><ps>INF.</ps><note>used as intensifier in verbal abuse; vulg.; off.</note><seealso>把𨶙 baa2 lan2, 𨶙蛋 lan2 daan6/2, 𨶙樣 lan2 joeng6/2, 戇𨶙𨳊 ngong6 lan2 gau1, 話𨶙之 waa6 lan2 zi1</seealso><df eid="10869_df_2" >fuck, fucking, damn</df><s1 n="2.1"><x-g ><tx eid="10869_tx_1" >咪攪𨶙我!</tx><x eid="10869_x_1" >Don't fuck with me!</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2.2"><x-g ><tx eid="10869_tx_2" >真麻𨶙煩!</tx><x eid="10869_x_2" >It's really damn troublesome!</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2.3"><x-g ><tx eid="10869_tx_3" >關你𨶙事咩!𨶙開!</tx><x eid="10869_x_3" >Is it any of your fucking business? Fuck off!</x></x-g></s1></s2><ser>10869</ser><ref>YH1972:246; ZC1988:204; BB1997:495; CB2002:120; HB2005:246</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10871" hw="lan2 daan6/2"><hw eid="10871_hw_1" >𨶙蛋</hw><ps>N.</ps><en>lit. prick egg; fig.; sl.; vulg. insult</en><seealso>𨶙 lan2, 𨶙樣 lan2 joeng6/2</seealso><df eid="10871_df_1" >fucking bastard</df><ser>10871</ser><ref>HB2005:246</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="10870" hw="lan2 joeng6/2"><hw eid="10870_hw_1" >𨶙樣</hw><ps>N.</ps><en>lit. prick face; fig.; sl.; vulg. insult</en><seealso>粉腸 fan2 coeng4/2, 𨶙 lan2, 𨶙蛋 lan2 daan6/2</seealso><df eid="10870_df_1" >fucking jerk</df><ser>10870</ser><ref>HB2005:246</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="13510" hw="lap6 faat3 wui6/2"><hw eid="13510_hw_1" >立法會</hw><ps>N.</ps><var>a.p.a. laap6 faat3 wui6/2; a.s.a. 立會 laap6 wui6/2, lap6 wui6/2; full fml. name is 香港特別行政區立法會 hoeng1 gong2 dak6 bit6 hang4 zing3 keoi1 lap6 faat3 wui6/2 'Legislative Council of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region'; orig. established in 1843 as a colonial legislature under Br. rule</var><seealso>特首 dak6 sau2, 地區直選 dei6 keoi1 zik6 syun2, 基本法 gei1 bun2 faat3, 功能界別 gung1 nang4 gaai3 bit6, 行政會議 hang4 zing3 wui6 ji5, 香港特別行政區 hoeng1 gong2 dak6 bit6 hang4 zing3 keoi1, 香港特別行政區基本法 hoeng1 gong2 dak6 bit6 hang4 zing3 keoi1 gei1 bun2 faat3, 垃圾局 laap6 saap3 guk6/2, 拉布 laai1 bou3, 剪布 zin2 bou3, 政務司司長 zing3 mou6 si1 si1 zoeng2</seealso><df eid="13510_df_1" >Legislative Council, a.k.a. LegCo, i.e. HK.'s legislature which enacts laws, approves the HK. govt.'s budget, monitors the HK. govt.'s work, etc.; in 2015 it comprised 70 members, 35 of whom had been elected by geographical constituencies and 35 by functional constituencies</df><s1 n="1"><x-g ><tx eid="13510_tx_1" >你真係嘥𨶙晒啲立法會時間!</tx><x eid="13510_x_1" >You're really fucking wasting completely the Legislative Council's time!</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2"><x-g ><tx eid="13510_tx_2" >嗰個立法會議員只不過係啲大班嘅扯線公仔</tx><x eid="13510_x_2" >That Legislative Council member is merely a puppet controlled by some tycoons</x></x-g></s1><ser>13510</ser><ref>CE2005:546; RSBfmInternet22082014; SKLC2014:154</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="04382" hw="lou5 hai1"><hw eid="04382_hw_1" >老閪</hw><ps>EXCL.</ps><en>lit. old cunt; vulg.; obsc.</en><seealso>閪 hai1, 老西 lou5 sai1, 呢鑊老西 ni1 wok6 lou5 sai1</seealso><df eid="04382_df_1" >I'm fucked</df><x-g ><tx eid="04382_tx_1" >老閪我知!</tx><x eid="04382_x_1" >I'm fucked if I know! (i.e. I admit my ignorance about it)</x></x-g><ser>04382</ser><ref>HB2005:263</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="11707" hw="man6 hau6 nei5 lou5 dau6"><hw eid="11707_hw_1" >問候你老豆</hw><ps>EUPH.</ps><en>lit. give my regards to your father; fig.; indirectly hostile exp. said to insult so.; used in place of 𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2 '(I) fuck your mother'</en><seealso>老豆 lou5 dau6, 問候你老母</seealso><df eid="11707_df_1" >go to hell</df><ser>11707</ser><ref>HB2005:281</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="11706" hw="man6 hau6 nei5 lou5 mou5/2"><hw eid="11706_hw_1" >問候你老母</hw><ps>EUPH.</ps><en>lit. give my regards to your mother; fig.; indirectly hostile exp. said to insult so.; used in place of 𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2 '(I) fuck your mother'</en><seealso>𨳒你老母 diu2 nei5 lou5 mou5/2, 老母 lou5 mou5/2, 問候你老豆 man6 hau6 nei5 lou5 dau6, 你老母 nei5 lou5 mou5/2</seealso><df eid="11706_df_1" >go to hell</df><x-g ><tx eid="11706_tx_1" >呢隻中指問候你老母!</tx><x eid="11706_x_1" >This middle finger is to give my regards to your mother (i.e. it means go to hell)!</x></x-g><ser>11706</ser><ref>HB2005:281; ZZF2008:092</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="07666" hw="m4 hou2 gam3 lan2 cyun3"><hw eid="07666_hw_1" >唔好咁𨶙串</hw><ps>IMPV.</ps><note>speaker criticizes the addressee's arrogant behavior; imp.</note><seealso>串 cyun3, 咁 gam3, 𨶙 lan2, 唔 m4, 唔好 m4 hou2</seealso><df eid="07666_df_1" >don't be so fucking arrogant</df><x-g ><tx eid="07666_tx_1" >我而𠺢警告你,呢個場一向都係我話晒事嘅,我做大時你做細,你唔好咁𨶙串啊!</tx><x eid="07666_x_1" >I'm now warning you, I've been completely in charge of this place all along. When I'm the big guy, and you're smallfry, so don't be so fucking arrogant!</x></x-g><ser>07666</ser><ref>HB2005:289; RSBfmInternet25022014</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="05451" hw="ngong6 lan2 gau1"><hw eid="05451_hw_1" >戇𨶙𨳊</hw><ps>S.V.</ps><en>lit. fucking stupid prick; vulg.</en><seealso>大懵 daai6 mung5/2, 大泡和 daai6 paau1 wo4, 癲癲廢廢 din1 din1 fai3 fai3, 𨳊 gau1, 𨶙 lan2, 矇查查 mung4 caa4 caa4, 懵閉閉 mung5/2 bai3 bai3, 懵懂 mung5/2 dung2, 懵懵哋 mung5/2 mung5/2 dei2, 懵盛盛 mung5/2 sing6 sing6, 𣲷油 nap6 jau4/2, 戇 ngong6, 戇𨳊 ngong6 gau1, 戇𨳊𨳊 ngong6 gau1 gau1, 戇啹 ngong6 geoi1, 戇啹啹 ngong6 geoi1 geoi1, 戇𨶙 ngong6 lan2, 霎戇 saap3 ngong6, 烏𡁷𡁷 wu1 doeng1 doeng1, 蒸生瓜 zing1 saang1 gwaa1</seealso><df eid="05451_df_1" >to be stupid, slow-witted, muddleheaded, incompetent</df><x-g ><tx eid="05451_tx_1" >你信嗰啲衰人,畀佢哋咁多錢?真係戇𨶙𨳊!</tx><x eid="05451_x_1" >You believed those scoundrels, and gave them that much money? How really fucking stupid you are!</x></x-g><ser>05451</ser><ref>HB2005:319</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="13290" hw="ngo5 zou6 daai6 si4 nei5 zou6 sai3"><hw eid="13290_hw_1" >我做大時你做細</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><en>lit. when I'm big you're little; fig.</en><df eid="13290_df_1" >when I'm the big guy you're the small fry</df><x-g ><tx eid="13290_tx_1" >我而𠺢警告你,呢個場一向我話晒事,我做大時你做細,你唔好咁𨶙串啊!</tx><x eid="13290_x_1" >I'm now warning you: I've been doing as I please in this place all along. When I'm the big guy, you're small fry, so don't be so fucking arrogant!</x></x-g><ser>13290</ser><ref>RSBfmInternet25022014</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="05752" hw="saai1"><hw eid="05752_hw_1" >嘥</hw><s3 n="1"><ps>V.</ps><var>a.w.a. 漇 saai1</var><seealso>阿崩吹簫 aa3 bang1 ceoi1 siu1, 大嘥 daai6 saai1, 大嘥鬼 daai6 saai1 gwai2, 大使 daai6 sai2, 嘥口水 saai1 hau2 seoi2, 嘥氣 saai1 hei3, 嘥料 saai3 liu6/2</seealso><s2 n="1.1"><df eid="05752_df_1" >to waste, squander, as money, time, food, water, electricity, talk, etc.</df><s1 n="1.1.1"><x-g ><tx eid="05752_tx_1" >佢嘥好多錢</tx><x eid="05752_x_1" >He wastes lots of money</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="1.1.2"><x-g ><tx eid="05752_tx_2" >你真係嘥𨶙晒啲議會時間!</tx><x eid="05752_x_2" >You're really fucking wasting completely the (Legislative) Council's time!</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="1.1.3"><x-g ><tx eid="05752_tx_3" >食得唔好嘥</tx><x eid="05752_x_3" >Eat as much as you can and don't waste any food</x></x-g></s1></s2><s1 n="1.2"><df eid="05752_df_2" >to pass up, miss, lose (an opportunity)</df><x-g ><tx eid="05752_tx_4" >有咁好嘅機會就唔好嘥啊</tx><x eid="05752_x_4" >Don't pass up such a good opportunity</x></x-g></s1></s3><s1 n="2"><ps>S.V.</ps><en>o.f.</en><df eid="05752_df_3" >to disparage or belittle so.; to deliberately underestimate so.</df><x-g ><tx eid="05752_tx_5" >你就算想自己出風頭,都唔使嘥人哋啩</tx><x eid="05752_x_5" >Even if you want to show off, there's no need to belittle other people</x></x-g></s1><ser>05752</ser><ref>MW1947:528; HPP1970:431; SL1977:673; GHN1984:312; CTA1997:075; WKB1997:232; BWR1998:106; ZN1999:281; ZBH2002a:261; CE2005:789; HB2005:339; KCW2008:566; ROZ2009:192; MT2011:186; SKLC2014:148</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="13553" hw="san1 gaai3 jyun4 geoi1 man4"><hw eid="13553_hw_1" >新界原居民</hw><ps>N.</ps><mw>個 go3</mw><seealso>村屋 cyun1 uk1, 丁 ding1, 丁權 ding1 kyun4, 丁屋 ding1 uk1, 丁屋政策 ding1 uk1 zing3 caak3, 鄉議局 hoeng1 ji5 guk6/2, 新界鄉村小型屋宇政策 san1 gaai3 hoeng1 cyun1 siu2 jing4 uk1 jyu5 zing3 caak3</seealso><df eid="13553_df_1" >indigenous inhabitant of the N.T., indigenous male villager in the N.t., i.e. a male resident (women are excluded) of the N.T. over the age of 18 and a descendant through the male line of so. who had inhabited the N.T. in (or before) 1898 (when Br. had begun its 99-year lease on the N.T.); a representative of a rural committee or village must verify that the man is a genuine indigenous villager; such inhabitants are guaranteed special rights to preserve their customs under Article 40 of HK.'s Basic Law</df><s1 n="1"><x-g ><tx eid="13553_tx_1" >每個新界原居民嘅男丁都有權利要求興建丁屋</tx><x eid="13553_x_1" >Every indigenous adult male inhabitant of the New Territories has the right to request to build a small house</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2"><x-g ><tx eid="13553_tx_2" >你試吓走入新界,話又要有丁權,要有地起屋,包畀人打𨳍你,掟番你出九龍,點解呢?因為你唔係新界原居民囉!</tx><x eid="13553_x_2" >You try to go to the New Territories, and say you want to have the right to build a small house, that you want land to build a house on. I guarantee you'll be fucking beaten up, and thrown back into Kowloon, Why? Because you're not an indigenous male inhabitant of the New Territories!</x></x-g></s1><ser>13553</ser><ref>TXL2009:242; RSBfmInternet23082014</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="13838" hw="sei2 ceon2 hai1"><hw eid="13838_hw_1" >死蠢閪</hw><ps>N.</ps><note>said to curse so., usu. a woman; vulg.; off.; obsc.</note><seealso>閪 hai1, 死 sei2</seealso><df eid="13838_df_1" >damn stupid cunt</df><x-g ><tx eid="13838_tx_1" >佢阿媽鬧佢死蠢閪,周街俾人𨳒!</tx><x eid="13838_x_1" >Her mother cursed her as a damn stupid cunt who'd been fucked all over the place!</x></x-g><ser>13838</ser><ref>RSBfmInternet18032015</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="11288" hw="sei2 lou5 je5"><hw eid="11288_hw_1" >死老嘢</hw><ps>N.</ps><mw>個 go3, 條 tiu4</mw><en>lit. dead old stuff; fig.; insulting; r.t. old man or woman</en><seealso>老鬼 lou5 gwai2, 老嘢 lou5 je5, 老而不 lou5 ji4 bat1, 死 sei2, 死老鬼 sei2 lou5 gwai2</seealso><df eid="11288_df_1" >damn old geezer, old shit, old bastard, damn old woman</df><x-g ><tx eid="11288_tx_1" >個單車友對個阿婆大聲嗌,你個死老嘢!亂𨶙噉過馬路!想害𨶙死我咩?</tx><x eid="11288_x_1" >The bicyclist yelled at the old lady, "You damn old woman! Fucking recklessly crossing the road like that! Do you want to fucking kill me?!"</x></x-g><ser>11288</ser><ref>HB2005:366; RSBfmInternet07122014</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="09266" hw="waa6 lan2 zi1"><hw eid="09266_hw_1" >話𨶙之</hw><ps>F.E.</ps><note>speaker exp. indifference; vulg.</note><seealso>𨶙 lan2, 話之 waa6 zi1</seealso><df eid="09266_df_1" >who gives a fuck!; never fucking mind!</df><ser>09266</ser><ref>HB2005:420</ref></entry> 
<entry eid="13283" hw="zi1 naa6/4 wong4 cung4"><hw eid="13283_hw_1" >支那蝗蟲</hw><ps>N.</ps><mw>啲 di1, 個 go3, 條 tiu4, 隻 zek3</mw><en>lit. China locusts; fig.; derog.; off.; 支那 zi1 naa6/4 comes orig. from the Jp. transliteration of China as しな shina and was used as a derog. term to replace the respectful and appropriate 中國 zung1 gwok3 'China' from the first Sino-Jp. war which ended in 1895 up through WWII; because of this word's derog. history, it has been deliberately used since 2012 by some HK. people who are alarmed by and resentful of the ever increasing nums. of mainland Ch. people who have been coming to HK. and taking its resources and benefits, and so they use it to r.t. the outsiders to disparagingly distinguish them from Hongkongers; a.s.a. 支那蟲 zi1 naa6/4 cung4, 支那蝗 zi1 naa6/4 wong4</en><seealso>北佬 bak1 lou2, 大陸人 daai6 luk6 jan4, 大陸佬 daai6 luk6 lou2, 鄉下佬 hoeng1 haa6/2 lou2, 嘮佬 laau1 lou2, 嘮鬆佬 laau1 sung1 lou2, 嘮頭 laau1 tau4, 外江人 ngoi6 gong1 jan4, 外江佬 ngoi6 gong1 lou2, 内地人 noi6 dei6 jan4, 蝗蟲 wong4 cung4, 支那人 zi1 naa6/4 jan4</seealso><df eid="13283_df_1" >tourists from mainland Ch. visting in HK.; per. from mainland Ch. in HK.</df><s1 n="1"><x-g ><tx eid="13283_tx_1" >支那蝗蟲死番大陸</tx><x eid="13283_x_1" >(actual text that was wrtn. on a HK. protestor's placard that was displayed during a public demonstration opposed to the large nums. of tourists from mainland Ch. in HK. that was held in Tsim Sha Tsui in February 2014) China locusts get the fucking hell back to mainland China</x></x-g></s1><s1 n="2"><x-g ><tx eid="13283_tx_2" >我真係忍受唔到宿舍嗰條支那蝗蟲啦!</tx><x eid="13283_x_2" >I really can't endure that China locust in the dormitory!</x></x-g></s1><ser>13283</ser><ref>RSBfmInternet18022014</ref></entry> 
